The mainframe is an ever-evolving platform.
It's one of the reasons we get to come back and re-record this video.
New features are constantly being developed,
existing components are getting upgrades,
and its capabilities are always being extended to meet the world's business demands.
As it evolves, the mainframe continues to gain unique capabilities
that you won't find anywhere else.
And last time, Jeff stood here and talked about the brand-new Z14
and ZOS version 2 release 2.
Today, a Z17 with ZOS 3.2 is the new hotness.
Point is, new is relative,
so we're going to talk about some new things,
but just understand, as long as time keeps doing its thing,
there will always be new new things.
There's three new things I really want to focus in on.
Of course, the ability to process AI models on the Tellum 2
and the Spire chip are huge.
And AI runs throughout everything on the system,
so let's look at some of the other highlights.
Let's start with IBM Concert for Z.
The job of an operator is to keep things running and stay invisible.
If people are thinking about the operator,
it's usually because something's going wrong,
so staying ahead of those situations is a good strategy.
IBM Concert for Z brings key performance indicators and metrics
to a single pane of glass.
So not just CPU and memory and events,
but the relationships between applications and resources.
So you won't just see what's happening,
you'll be able to detect trends before they become problems.
And then, once we see something we know we need to act on,
not only is there an integrated command console,
there's AI-driven root cause detection and built-in recommendations,
which is great.
You get to start with a heads-up in a series of recommendations.
And of course, I'm not jealous at all of this.
I'm happy for you.
Really.
It's not about me.
Let's move on.
How about quantum-safe cryptography?
In the world of data,
there's not very much these days that travels out over a network
or between entities without being encrypted at one end
before being decrypted at the other.
This is done by using a series of public and private keys.
Those same keys are used to authenticate our communications.
The entire public-private key ecosystem relies on two things.
Those private keys remaining private and the encryption being so strong
that even if someone did manage to intercept a few packets of data,
they wouldn't be able to peek inside.
Here's the problem.
Today's sophisticated hackers are out there gathering that encrypted data,
knowing that it may only be a few years before they get their hands on the tools to decrypt it.
They're playing the long game here.
And you may have heard figures about how it would take thousands
or even millions of years to crack a properly encrypted key.
But most of those figures are based on classical computing methods.
Shores algorithm, a method for finding prime factors of an integer
is a good example of something that runs very slowly on today's computers,
but could be greatly accelerated once quantum computing advances in several areas.
Long story short, the technology we consider ultra secure today
could fall apart in the face of quantum computing,
which is why quantum-safe cryptography on IBM Z provides not only
algorithms and key exchange mechanisms with this emerging threat in mind.
It also provides the tools to analyze your environment for potential exposures,
facilitate the rollout of quantum-safe algorithms,
and ensure keys are rotated and managed based on policy.
Those tools include the ZOS encryption readiness toolkit,
ZERT, application discovery and delivery intelligence,
ADDI, and unified key orchestrator.
There's also something you really ought to be aware of,
which is still fairly new, called system recovery boost.
This is a favorite of mine.
So your typical mainframe is meant to be used.
It's built with a capacity in mind, and any time it's not running applications,
it's costing someone money.
So it's important to keep those windows as brief as possible.
Now, let me also say that most IBM Z environments
will have multiple L-Pars across multiple physical systems and assist blocks,
so they can do what's called a rolling IPL.
So we're working on these two systems, and then these two systems,
and when we work on these last two systems,
everything's got maintenance, and we always had at least six systems ready to go.
But even then, we don't want to spend all day doing these rolling IPLs,
and we also want to spend as little time with a decreased pool of systems as possible.
That's where system recovery boost comes in.
During what is called the boost period, the system is allowed to use processors,
which are typically off limits, reserved for specialty workloads,
in order to get everything running at full capacity again as quickly as possible.
That's the technology part of this.
The other part that makes the people with the calculators happy,
is that during the boost period, all that extra power doesn't increase software licensing costs.
It's just there to help shorten that window.
The features we just went through are interesting and exciting to me right now.
The real important lesson here is to stay up to date.
IBM.com slash Z will give you the latest on software, hardware,
design, security, services, everything.
So don't stop with what we've covered. Keep going, keep learning.